第三集：哺乳动物
南极
Antarctica.
地球上最寒冷地方
The earth's coldest continent,
极度不适合生物生存
the one that is most hostile to life.
这里，距离南极点800英里
Here, 800 miles from the South Pole,
零下40摄氏度
it's 40 degrees below zero.
地球上数百万种动物中
Of all the millions of species of animals on Earth,
只有一种能一直在此生存
only one can live here permanently.
威德尔海豹
A Weddell seal.
它能生存是因为可以潜到冰层下面
She can survive because she can dive below the ice.
使自己不受上面的暴风雪袭击
Here she is protected from the storms above,
这里也能找到食物
and here too, she can find food.
但它是哺乳动物，必须呼吸空气
But she is a mammal,and she has to breathe air,
所以它必须守住一条通到冰层上面的生命线
so she has to keep a lifeline open to the world above the ice.
不只是为自己
Not only for her,
也为刚出生的幼仔
but now for her newborn pup.
SEAL GRUNTS
PUP CRIES
它还没一周大，仍旧很脆弱
He's less than a week old,
and still very vulnerable.
暴风雪来袭，力量强劲
A blizzard blows in,
and with it, storm-force winds.
可以持续一周
It could last for a week.
作为哺乳类，海豹可以体内产热
Being mammals, seals can generate
heat within their bodies.
皮毛下面是一层厚厚的脂肪
And their fur, with
a thick layer of fat beneath it,
能防止绝大多数的热量散失
prevents most of that heat from escaping,
即便是在这么冷的情况下
even in cold conditions like this.
更重要的是，它能用哺乳动物所特有的
What is more,she is able to feed her youngster
乳汁，来哺育后代
with that mammalian speciality,milk.
哺乳时，它还为幼仔遮挡住暴风雪
And while she does so, she shields
him from the worst of the blizzard.
整个冬天，它都孜孜不倦地工作
She has worked hard throughout the
winter to prevent her breathing hole
防止通气孔被冰冻封住
in the ice from freezing over.
这需要持久的专注
That requires constant attention -
用牙齿清除洞周围的冰
filing back the edges of the hole with her teeth.
一旦幼仔长到适合游泳，就得跟它一起下水
Her pup needs to join her under the
ice as soon as he can swim properly.
它鼓励它第一次下水
She encourages him to take his first plunge, but,
奇怪的是，它一点也不紧张
hardly surprisingly, he is not keen.
现在，在妈妈的指导下，它要学习如何在水下捕食
Now, guided by his mother, he has to learn how to hunt underwater,
同时能够在水下迷宫里找到返回通气孔的路
and to find his way back through the maze to his hole in the ice.
体温、皮毛、乳汁以及母亲的呵护
A warm body, fur, milk and maternal care are essential
是海豹在这严寒里生存必不可少的
for the Weddell seal's survival in this freezing environment.
这些特点有助哺乳动物
And those qualities have helped the mammals
统治整个地球
to colonise the entire globe.
东非赤道地带
Equatorial East Africa.
是一个与南极洲完全不同的世界
It's hard to image a place more different from Antarctica.
要在这里生存，哺乳类需要额外的智慧
To survive here,mammals need additional talents.
这三个窝点是一种小动物的领地
This tree shelters the territory of a tiny mammal
花费了它毕生的精力辛勤打理
that spends its whole life in frenzied activity.
以前被称作长鼻
It used to be called an elephant shrew,
现在有个非洲化的名字：森吉（扎伊尔硬币）
but now it's called by its African name of sengi.
这是一只红褐色的雌性sengi
This is a female rufous sengi.
就像所有的sengi一样，它太活跃，总是吃不饱
And, like all sengis, she's so active, she's permanently hungry.
为了得到足够的食物
To get all the food she needs,
它必须勤劳而又灵巧
she has to be both industrious and ingenious.
它为设计了错综复杂的路线
She has made an intricate network of trails
帮助自己有效地猎食昆虫
that enable her to hunt her insect prey very efficiently.
但这些通道在遭遇天敌时
But these pathways have another important function
有重要的作用
when she meets her enemies.
能否在头脑中牢记这张路线图关系着
Having a map of these trails
in her head can mean the difference
生存
between life...
或死亡
..and death.
跟爬行类不同，像大多数哺乳类
Like most mammals,and unlike reptiles,
它的腿长在身体正下方（爬行类在身体两侧）
her legs are directly
beneath her body.
这使它不太稳定，但是更加迅速灵巧
That makes her less stable,
but much faster and more agile.
它不但比这只蜥蜴跑得快，更比它聪明
Not only has she outrun this reptile, she's outwitted him.
还有
And just as well,
它是一位需要照顾幼仔的母亲
for she is a mother and has a youngster to care for.
sengi依靠速度和智谋取得成功
The sengi relies on speed and cunning for its success.
其它的哺乳类有不同的技能
Other mammals have very different techniques.
ANIMALS CALL OUT
马达加斯加
Here in Madagascar,
一种最为怪异的哺乳动物正在游荡
one of the most bizarre of all mammals is on the prowl.
长指狐猴，跟sengi一样，吃昆虫
The aye-aye, like the sengi,lives on insects.
但它看不见所找的食物
But the ones that she seeks,she can't see,
因为它们躲在树干深处
for they're buried deep inside branches.
它们是挖虫高手
They're beetle grubs.
为找到食物，它有特殊天分
To find them,she has a special talent.
它用手指以每秒8次的速度敲击树干
She taps her fingers on the
wood up to eight times a second,
通过分辨回声中的细微差别
and listens for the tiny change in resonance
侦测出里面是否有洞
that indicates a hollow spot within.
它的听力及其灵敏，能准确定位
Her hearing is so acute, she can
identify the precise position
然后咬开树皮，找到虫子
in which to gnaw a hole in order to reach the grub.
用它变态的超长中指
And she has a grotesquely long middle finger
刺入洞中抓虫
with which to skewer it.
长指狐猴要花费四年时间来完善这种技能
It takes a young aye-aye four
years to perfect this technique.
一旦练成
But once it has done so,
它就能得到别人吃不到的食物
it can collect prey that no other mammal can reach.
北极冻原
The Arctic tundra.
这里也很难找到食物
Food is hard to find here too.
实际上，这片土地太过贫瘠，极少有大型动物能在这里生存
Indeed, this land is so barren
that few large animals can live here.
但有一种哺乳动物可以做到
Yet one mammal has found a way to do so.
晚春
It's late spring,
太阳温暖大地
and as the mounting strength
of the sun warms the land,
约8百万只驯鹿向北迁移
eight million reindeer move north.
但是草木太过稀少
But the vegetation is so meagre
鹿群想要吃饱，就必须
that the only way the herds can get enough
一路吃下去
is to keep constantly on the move.
新生小鹿很快就发觉
Newborn calves soon discover
它们必须每天赶路找吃的
that they will have to spend
every day walking in search of food.
它们有着惊人的耐受力
They have extraordinary endurance.
这种动物在死之前
Some of these animals,before they die,
已经走了很长的路
will have trekked for a distance
足够绕地球三周
equivalent to three times around the earth.
现在的牧场是最好的
Grazing is now at its best.
但驯鹿们最讨厌的敌人,也在此时现身
But this also the time when the reindeer' worst enemy appears...
BUZZING
吸血蝇
Biting flies.
苍蝇不但扰得它们心烦意乱
The flies not only drive them to distraction,
而且每天可以吸掉它们一品脱的血
but they can drain a pint of blood each day.
驯鹿们有一种防御策略
But the reindeer have a defensive strategy.
每一只都尽力朝群体中心靠拢
Each individual tries to push its way into the centre of a group
在那里苍蝇很少
where there are fewer flies.
所有的鹿挤在一起
With all this pushing and jostling,
母亲们必须盯紧自己的孩子
mothers need to keep their calves close.
有时候苍蝇太过分了
Sometimes the flies become so bad
鹿群实在无法忍受
the reindeer can stand them no longer
它们都逃向苍蝇们无法跟随的高地
and they bolt to higher ground
where the flies can't follow.
但这种逃避也有代价
But the price of escape can be high.
慌乱中，一个鹿妈妈丢失了她的孩子
In the rush,one mother has lost her calf.
REINDEER CALLS OUT
已经被别的生物找到了
Others have already found it.
BIRDS CALL OUT
鹿群照旧前进
The herd has long since moved on,
但它母性本能十分强烈
but her maternal instinct is so strong
它会留下来好几天，寻找丢失的孩子
she'll stay to search for her missing calf for days.
鹿群现在摆脱了苍蝇的困扰
The reindeer are free from flies for now,
但在这高山上没有食物
but with no food on these high slopes,
它们将会被迫下山寻找草场
they will eventually be forced
to descend to find new pastures
再一次面对吸血蝇
and face the biting swarms once more.
地球上没有哪种动物比它们
No animal makes a longer migration across the lands of the earth
迁徙的更远了
than these mammals.
有些生物找到了一种更经济的方式
Other mammals have found a more economic way
进行更快速的远距离迁徙
of travelling huge distances and at greater speed.
它们用飞的
They go by air.
BIRDS CHIRP
巨大的食果黄蝙蝠
Giant straw-coloured fruit bats
栖居于刚果森林
inhabit the great forests of the Congo.
它们的翼展达一米
Their wings are nearly a metre across.
每年十月下旬
In late October every year,
它们动身越过森林，进行长途旅行
they set off on a long journey across the forest canopy.
从几百只到几千只
Flocks of hundreds become thousands.
然后几万、几十万
And tens of thousands become hundreds of thousands.
它们是快速而强健的飞行家
They are fast and powerful fliers
几个晚上就可以飞出上千英里
and can travel a thousand miles in just a few nights.
THUNDER RUMBLES
它们如何确定出发时间以及目的地仍旧是个谜
How they know where and when to travel is a mystery,
但它们都在同一地方落脚：卡桑卡，赞比亚的一个偏远沼泽
but they all end up in one place -
Kasanka, a remote swamp in Zambia.
这里约有一千万只蝙蝠
There are ten million of them here.
它们在差不多有两三个足球场大的
They crowd together in just one small patch of forest,
一小片丛林里聚集
no bigger than two or three football pitches.
在此逗留几星期
And here they take up residence for a few weeks.
这里成了地球上最大的食果蝙蝠栖息地
It's the largest fruit bat roost on Earth.
经过长途跋涉，它们需要休息
After their long journey,they need to rest and relax.
这里实在太挤，几乎肩靠着肩
The roost is so crowded that complete strangers rub shoulders,
甚至互相抱成一团
and even snuggle up together.
夜幕降临
As evening approaches,
它们准备享用长途旅行的奖赏
they prepare to reap the reward for their long journey.
它们越过中非来到这里
They've come from all over
Central Africa to this one place,
因为
because here,
在每年此时
at this time of the year,
这里的芒果，还有其它果实正好丰收
there is an extraordinary glut of mangoes and other fruit.
它们如潮水般涌出，去搜集食物
Streaming out from the roost,they set off to collect it.
每只蝙蝠一晚上，可以狂吞约两公斤的水果
Each bat guzzles at least two kilos' worth of fruit every night.
几周下来，这一群
In just a few weeks, this mega-roost
将会吃下多达十亿只水果
will devour more than a billion separate fruits.
也只因具备飞行的能力，它们才能
It's only the power of flight that allows these mammals
如此千里迢迢赶来，大吃一顿
to travel so far and so fast that
they can reap such a brief harvest.
六周过后，树上的果子被吃个精光
After six weeks, the trees have been stripped of their fruit.
然后，这支庞大的空军又起飞
Then, once again, the immense
aerial armada takes to the air,
各自回到原来
each bat returning to its own particular patch
位于刚果丛林的栖息地
of the vast Congo forests.
非洲的陆生哺乳动物
The land mammals of Africa
也进行大规模的迁徙
also travel together in stupendous numbers.
东非草原上的动物数量
The herds that graze the East African plains
比一个世纪前要少了很多
are not nearly the size they were a century ago,
但仍旧很庞大
but they are still immense.
聚在一起是很好的防御策略
Grazing together is a good defence.
以数量取胜
There's safety in numbers.
集体捕猎也会带来好处
But hunting together also brings advantages.
LION SNARLS
这只鬣狗，却在独自觅食
This hyena, however,is searching for food on her own.
它得小心
She needs to be careful.
但是它闻到了食物的味道
But she smells food.
决定冒险
And she takes risks.
HYENA YOWLS
HYENA SHRIEKS
皮开肉绽，它很幸运地在犯错后活了下来
Bruised and bloodied, she is
lucky to have survived her mistake.
但它并没有被完全打败
But she's not totally defeated -
它是一个家族的成员
she belongs to a clan.
夜间，战斗的嚎叫响彻四方
A call to arms rings out through the night.
HYENA CALLS OUT
集结号
Reinforcements assemble.
家族里成年的个体作出回应
Every adult in the clan responds.
如果一个家族一起攻击，它们可以挑战那几头狮子
If a clan attack together, they have
a chance of challenging the lions.
HYENAS CALL OUT
LION SNARLS
一群鬣狗挑战一个狮群，双方都全力以赴
It's a clan against a pride,each at full strength.
鬣狗数量上占优势
And the clan outnumbers the pride.
鬣狗们的强势
The combined power of the hyenas
最终逼得狮子们撤退
eventually forces the lions to retreat.
有组织地进行团队作战
Attacking as a coherent team
需要高度的社会合作能力
requires a high degree of social cooperation,
这也是哺乳动物的另一专长
and that is another of the mammals' specialities.
动物间的联系
Social bonds between mammals begin
在母亲哺育后代时就开始建立
when mothers feed their young on milk.
加上对幼小后代极好的照顾
And few look after their young with greater care
哺乳动物统治了自然
than the mammal which dominates this landscape.
一头母北极熊设正法为幼仔找食物
A female polar bear is trying to find food for her cubs.
但这是一年中
But this is a particularly
特别艰难的时日
difficult time of the year.
供觅食的冰面正在开始融化
The sea ice on which she hunts
is melting beneath her feet.
它必须上岸
She must look for food on land.
它们都安全上岸，但还需面临几个月的饥荒
They're all safely ashore, but they
could still face months of hunger.
在这寒冷贫瘠的海岸，寻找食物实在太难
Finding food is not so easy
on this cold and barren coast.
搜寻过程很漫长
The search may be a long one.
北极熊有着异常敏锐的嗅觉
Polar bears have an extraordinarily
sensitive sense of smell.
它嗅到了一丝希望
And she has caught a faint whiff of something promising.
是一具巨大的北极露脊鲸的尸体
It's the immense carcass of a bowhead whale.
这具尸体可供这一家子吃好长时间
A whale carcass could provide
more than any one family could eat.
但毕竟不是它们
But they're not the first here to find it...
最先发现的
by any means.
气味将远处的熊都引来了
The smell has brought in bears from miles away.
ROARING
北极熊一家很少与另一家相处
Bear families seldom get on with one another.
所以，带小熊来这里很冒险
She's taking a risk bringing her cubs here.
公熊可能，也确实会杀死，吃掉小熊
Male bears can, and do,kill and eat small cubs.
ROARING
另一家向它挑战
Another family challenges her.
它必须决定，是继续争夺食物
还是带着孩子逃跑，然后挨饿
She must decide whether to compete
for food, or run away and go hungry.
它将幼仔护在自己身边，守住地盘
She keeps her cubs close to her and stands her ground.
母亲的勇气为孩子挣来一餐
Their mother's courage has won the cubs a meal.
群居生活可以带来回报
Living as a family may bring rewards,
但也会带来麻烦，因为兄弟姐妹之间会竞争
but it can also create problems,
for siblings can also become rivals.
南美长鼻浣熊
A coati - a South American relative of the racoon.
这些小家伙是在树上的窝里出生的
These babies were born in a nest high in a tree,
现在第一次下地
and are about to come down to
the ground for the first time.
有些很排斥其它的浣熊
Some more reluctantly than others.
一旦到了地面，母亲会把小仔们聚在一起
Once on the ground, the mother coati rounds her babies up
形成一个大的群体
and takes them away to join a single large group.
一个家庭有40多个成员
Together, these families form a gang up to 40 strong.
数量多就安全
Once again, numbers bring safety.
最先觉察到危险的会警告所有的
The first to spot danger will warn everyone.
但维持秩序就不容易了
But keeping order isn't easy,
一旦发现食物，熊熊有份
and when they find food,it's a free-for-all.
卡拉哈利沙漠的猫鼬
Meerkats in the Kalahari Desert
也是群体生活，但它们更有组织性
also live in large groups,but they are rather more organised.
每个家族被一位年长雌性所掌控
Each family band is controlled by a queen,
几乎是唯一的有生育能力的
who is nearly always the only female to breed.
它一直忙碌于哺育5个小仔
She has been kept very busy suckling her five pups,
它们是时候该独立自主了
and it's high time they became more independent.
今天是这些新生儿第一次自己找早餐
Today is the new brood's first trip
to get breakfast for themselves.
新手们要花好几周学习如何找食物
It takes weeks for youngsters to learn how to find food.
MEERKAT SQUEAKS
这个家伙试图抓蚂蚁
This one is trying to catch ants,
但还没掌握必需的技巧
but hasn't quite grasped the necessary technique.
但这个小家伙说服了一个年长的，示范该怎么做
But this youngster has persuaded an adult to show him what to do.
导师并不是父母，只是有了热情
The tutor is not his parent,just an enthusiastic instructor,
通过教学将能力传给学生
and one who will adapt his lessons to the ability of his student.
这个是初学者
This new one is a beginner,
所以从简单的开始，如何挖出一只昆虫幼虫
so he starts with something easy -how to dig for insect larvae.
另一位，如这个，则棘手的多
Other meals, like this one,are much trickier.
老师在让它对付蝎子之前
So the tutor disables the scorpion's sting
会先搞定它的毒刺
before he
lets the youngster tackle it.
家族也会协同防御
The family also cooperates in defence.
每一位都会轮流站岗，留心危险
Every member does a tour of guard
duty, keeping an eye out for danger.
所以，只要有一只放哨
So, while one watches,
其它的都可以放松
everyone else can rest.
在大热天里，很容易打盹
And, on warm days,one can easily nod off.
猫鼬的成功奥秘在于
The secret of meerkats' success
每一位都轮流站岗
is that everyone takes a turn in communal duties.
许多哺乳类不止是分担工作量
But many mammals do more
than just share their workload.
还可以通过好几代来分享智慧
Some can share their knowledge,
and do so across several generations.
大象的生存得益于
Elephant survival depends on profiting
好多代传下来的经验
from the experience of many lifetimes.
这只小象是昨晚才出生的
This baby elephant was born last night,
整个家族都很欢迎它的加入
and the whole herd seems to welcome this new addition.
但这位母亲很年轻，经验不足
But the mother is young and inexperienced.
这是它第一个孩子
This is her first baby.
母亲必须喝水，才能产奶
If she is to produce milk,a mother must drink.
新生儿则要跟着它
And the newborn calf must keep up with her
象群走上了寻找水源的路
as the herd continues on their long journey to find water.
走了五英里，小象很疲惫
After five miles,the calf is flagging.
走够了
Enough is enough.
年轻的母亲鼓励它继续
The young mother encourages her calf to continue,
但前路仍旧漫长
but there is still a long way to go,
小象已经开始脱水
and the calf is already getting dehydrated.
现在象群已经离水不远了，可以嗅到水的味道
The elephants are now so close
to water that they can smell it.
终于到了
Water, at last.
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
这是小象第一次遇到水坑
This is the calf's first
encounter with a waterhole.
它不确定是怎么回事，也不知道怎么爬出来
She's not sure what to make of it
or, indeed, how to get out of it.
母亲试图帮助它
Her mother tries to help her,
但它没有带孩子的经验
but she has no experience of dealing with babies.
（小象哭喊）
BABY ELEPHANT CRIES OUT
小象跟着象群朝沼泽深处前进
As the herd moves deeper into
the swamp, the calf follows,
现在，它真的麻烦大了
but now she is in real trouble.
（小象哭喊）
BABY ELEPHANT CRIES OUT
小象有可能会永远地陷入泥潭
Elephant babies can, and do, get
permanently stuck in deep mud.
母亲试图帮助它，但只会越帮越糟糕
Her mother's attempts to help her
baby are only making matters worse.
会让它越陷越深
It's stuck beneath her and
she's pushing it deeper still.
这时孩子的祖母发现了问题，走了过来
But now the baby's grandmother
spots the problem and steps in.
MUFFLED THUMP
MOTHER TRUMPETS
直截了当,它用象牙在后面戳了一下
Drastic action!She pushes mother out of the way
将孩子妈妈推向一边
with an unceremonious poke in the rump,
使得它的孙子能够爬出来
and enables her granddaughter to scramble free.
母亲和小孩从祖母那里学来重要一课
Mother and calf have learned
a valuable lesson from grandma.
智慧像这样代代相传
Such passing of wisdom across generations
是大象能够生存的重要基础
has been an important element
in the survival of elephants.
最大的陆生动物大象，是哺乳类
The largest animal on land,the elephant is a mammal.
海洋里最大的动物也同样是哺乳类
And so are the largest animals in the sea.
雌性驼背鲸和它的孩子
A female humpback whale and her calf.
每隔几年，它都会游过3000英里
Every few years,she will travel 3,000 miles,
从南极富饶的水域
from the rich waters of the Antarctic
到太平洋的温暖但是食物稀少的地区
to these warm, but comparatively
sterile, waters of the Pacific
产下一只幼仔
to give birth to a single calf.
汤加周围的海域，不止是驼背鲸的育儿所
The seas around Tonga are not only a nursery for humpbacks,
也是它们的交配场所
but also their mating ground.
WHALE CALLS OUT
这头50岁的母鲸来这里，寻找最佳配偶
This 50-year-old female has come
here to seek the best partner,
它开始对潜在的追求者宣告自己的到来
and she starts by announcing
her arrival to potential suitors.
异性一个个到来
One by one, the males arrive.
但它却游走了
But as they do, she swims away,
使得六头追随者跟着
compelling her half a dozen or so suitors to follow her.
它领头，雄性们则在后面抢位置
She leads, while the males jockey for position behind her.
WHALE BELLOWS
雄性们互相吼叫着示威
The males bellow threats to one another,
弄出巨大的水花
creating huge plumes of bubbles.
直到现在，一切还算公平、缓和
So far, it has been a relatively gentle affair.
眼下竞争变得严峻
Now the competition becomes serious.
一小时一小时过去，雄性在它后面抢位置
Hour after hour, the males battle for position, right behind her.
40多吨重的鲸们开始互相撞击
And now the 40-tonne males begin to smash into one another.
这是自然界最大块头的战斗
This is the most massive battle in all nature.
它们可以使对手致死
Rival males can kill one another.
在战斗最为激烈时
As the conflict reaches its climax,
它们希望对手都屈服
they try to force each other downwards.
最后，胜者将会陪伴在母鲸身边
At last, a victor takes his place alongside the female
不会再有不服
and remains unchallenged.
通过诱使雄性们决斗
By inciting the males to fight,
母鲸可以确保找到最佳的伴侣
the female has secured
the best mate for herself -
从而能够产下最强的后代
the one who is most likely
to father the strongest offspring.
夫妻双双潜入深处
Together,the couple dive to the depths.
但直到现在也没人知道它们在哪里交配
But still,no-one knows where they will mate.
所有哺乳动物，包括我们
All mammals, including ourselves,
都有一系列领先的特征
share a set of winning characteristics.
恒温的身体、敏锐的感官和高度发达的智力
Warm bodies, extraordinary senses
and highly-developed intelligence -
这些特质帮助它们，和我们，成功
and those qualities have contributed
to their, and our, success.
也许，所有特征里最重要的
But perhaps the most important characteristic of all
是来自我们的家庭力量
lies in the strength of our family ties.
哺乳动物是以家族的方式占领地球的
It is the mammal family
that has conquered the earth.
汤加，以驼背鲸闻名
Tonga is famous for humpback whales,
但即便在这儿，想找到并拍摄鲸
but even here, finding and filming whales in the open ocean
也是不小的挑战
would prove challenging.
Life摄制组想要
For the Life team,
拍到驼背鲸独特而著名的
capturing the humpback whales'unique mating contest,
求爱竞赛
known as a heat run,
需要花大量时间、当地的知识和超好的运气
would need local knowledge, hours on
the water, and a big slice of luck.
我们听说靠近陆地的一只船
We've heard that one of the boats further inland
见过一头带幼仔的母鲸和一批追随者
has seen a female with a calf and an escort,
这极有可能处于发情期
which is something which might
build to, hopefully, a heat run,
所以我们朝那边赶，去看看
so we're gonna head over there and take a look.
任何一头带小孩的母鲸都有可能出镜
Any adult female with a calf could be coming into season,
还会是发情的公鲸们的目标
and so might be a target for amorous males.
到那里时，我非常兴奋
When we got there, I was pretty excited,
也有点紧张，不知道会发生什么
a little bit nervous,didn't know what to expect.
一旦我潜到水里
Once I got in the water and dived down,
一片安静祥和
it was surprisingly quiet and mellow.
当然没预料到接下来的事
Certainly didn't expect what happened next.
那头小鲸直接冲我而来
The calf just came straight up towards me.
它看上去很放松，对我很有兴趣
She seemed really relaxed,
and definitely interested in me.
就在我周围几米处游动，轻轻摇尾巴
It's literally just swimming
around within metres of them,
我想，它应该很好奇吧
flicking its tail,just being inquisitive I think,
也有点好玩
and having a bit of fun.
确实还很小
It's obviously quite young,
所以在水面呆的时间很长
so it's staying on the surface quite a long time.
不能下潜很久
It's not diving down for very long,
大概几分钟吧，它母亲
maybe a couple of minutes.The mother will be
会在下面5到10米处看守着
about five or ten metres below just keeping an eye on it.
但即便是幼鲸，鳍和尾巴仍旧力量十足
But even a calf has great power in its fins and tail.
Roger需要小心为妙
Roger will need to be careful.
接着
Got it?
这是我见过的最荒诞的事情
That was the most silly thing I've ever seen in my life.
它在周围玩耍，就像新生羔羊
It was just gambolling around like a little newborn lamb.
但它有两吨重啊
But it's two tonnes.
THEY LAUGH
它朝我搅了些水流什么的
Couple of bumps as it's come round,
splashed his fluke at me or whatever.
Jason，我拍到了一些画面
I got a great shot of it, Jason.
Jason后仰成这样了
Jason was backpedalling like this!
只是头幼鲸，还小呢
It's just a baby.Like a little puppy,
你在和一个小动物玩，但是有四米长
you're playing with a little
puppy, but it's four metres long.
很荒谬吧，它妈妈怎么样？
It's just ludicrous.Was his mum all right?
它在下面怪吓人的
She is just totally chilling out underneath.
在水下15米处像这样悬停着
Pecs back. Just hanging like this at about 15 metres.
是的，只是悬在那里
Yeah, just hanging there.
或许是没看见，但我不这么认为
Probably didn't even see it,I don't think.
和贪玩的小鲸一起是一回事儿
It's one thing to be close to a playful baby.
但和一群雄激素水平超高的
It will be another to be in the path
体型是它十倍的雄性鲸
of a testosterone-charged group of males,
是另一回事
each ten times her size.
MUTTERED CONVERSATION
这里有很多雄性鲸，但它们发情了吗？
There are enough males here for a
heat run, but are they in the mood?
Oh!
Woo-hoo! Yes!
真不错
That was pretty good.
你们准备好了吗
When you guys are ready.
越快越好
Quick as you can.
这些鲸体重可达40吨，而且速度奇快
These whales can weigh up to 40
tonnes and move surprisingly quickly.
摄影机拍到好的画面
As well as getting the camera to get the shots -
得跟它们足够接近
they have to be fairly close -
我们必须小心，不要被撞到
we have to be careful they don't get bumped.
如果被它们撞一下
If they get a knock from one of these guys,
会造成严重的损害
it could do some serious damage.
它朝你过来了
He's right towards you.
为了不影响鲸的行为
To avoid disturbing the whales' behaviour,
组员们必须自由潜水，不带呼吸器
the team need to free-dive,without scuba tanks,
尽可能地憋气
holding their breath as long as they can.
状态好的话，我可以憋气两分钟
On a good dive, I can hold my breath for maybe two minutes.
但这些家伙，可以憋住20多分钟
These guys,they can go for 20 minutes or more
然后再到水面换气
before they have to come up for air.
没法比
There's no contest.
越来越多的鲸聚集过来
More and more whales are gathering,
但还没有达到发情状态
but it's not turning into a heat run yet.
很难说发生了什么
Hard to say what's going on.
是不是有5头？
Were there five that time?
它们只是游来游去，忽上忽下
They're kind of moving around,coming up and under and over.
可望有事发生
Hopefully,something's starting to happen.
莫非爱情在空中？
Maybe love's in the air?
HE CHUCKLES
爱情也许是在空中，但水里是没有的
Love may be in the air,but it isn't in the water.
接下来十天里，尽管一直跟着这些鲸
Despite keeping tabs on the whales over the next ten days,
但仍旧不见它们发情的迹象
there was still no sign of a heat run starting.
你也许会认为，跟踪这些40多吨的家伙很容易
You'd think it'd be quite easy to keep track of a 40-tonne animal.
我们一路跟着六头过来
And we've got six of them out here,
不断地跟丢，一分钟前它们还在这里
and we keep losing them.One minute they're there,
然后我们靠近
we get up reasonably close,
不到半分钟，它们又潜下去，失踪了
and within 30 seconds, they've dived and they're gone again.
然后，再等五到十分钟
And then it takes another maybe five minutes, ten minutes,
它们会在300多码外又再次出现
and then they'll come up again and they'll be 300 yards away,
然后又得花很长时间跟进
and it takes ages just to get close to them.
一直跟我们在玩猫捉老鼠的游戏
So we're just playing a continuous game of cat and mouse.
猫和老鼠？它们是鲸鱼哦
Cat and mouse? It's whales.
眼看繁殖季节就要结束了
The mating season is coming to an end,
制作组还没完成拍摄任务呢
and the crew haven't completed their mission.
最后，那些鲸的行为看起来有变化
But then, at last, the whales'
behaviour seems to have changed.
好，这就是了
Well, this is it!
我们在远处地平线发现了六到七头鲸
We just spotted about six or seven humpbacks on the horizon.
我们认为那就是求爱竞赛
We think it's a heat run.
在水上的最后16、17天
The last 16, 17 days on the water
取决于接下来两小时
are probably gonna come down to the next two hours,
我们能否拍到画面
as to whether we get our shots or not.
追逐开始了
The chase is on!
至少有三、四头鲸游过
There was at least three or four males going past -
它们互相争斗、互相撞击
they were competing and knocking into each other
尽力抢得母鲸后面的位置
as they tried to get the poll position behind the female.
朝你过来了，冲你过来了
It's right at you,it's right at you.
鲸游得太快了，想要找机会拍到它们
The whales are moving so fast that,
to stand any chance of filming them,
组员们必须在它们正前方入水
the crew needs to be dropped right in front of the charging group.
正当Roger来到鲸的旁边
Just as Roger gets alongside the males,
拍摄追逐的画面，忽然被
the tempo of the chase suddenly shifts to full bore
一个摆尾扰乱
with a flick of a tail.
面对发情的雄鲸，Roger在水下持续拍摄
Facing the charging males deep underwater, Roger keeps shooting,
屏住呼吸直到它们游过
holding his breath until the group pass over.
然后迅速上来换口气，又继续下水
A quick gasp of air, and Roger's back down again.
鲸们鱼贯而过
The whales continue to rush by.
最后，Roger实在是憋不住了
In the end,Roger just can't keep up any longer.
精疲力竭，他们最后一次回到了船上
Exhausted, it's time to return to the boat for the last time.
惊奇！实在是我最惊讶的一次经历
Amazing! That was the most amazing experience I've ever had.
大约有
There was about...
七到八头鲸，在前面水下20米左右
seven or eight. Both dived down about 20 metres in front.
雌性先游过来，很近
And then the female came through first, quite close.
然后它们都一下子朝我冲过来
And then they all just started diving towards me,
就像面对着车流一样
it was like standing in a stream of traffic.
这边一头，这边一头，另一边也有
It was just one one side, one
the next side, one the next side.
再过了约40秒
And then, after about 40 seconds,
45秒的样子，我有点透不过气来
40, 45 seconds, I was getting a little bit out of breath.
我向上看，头顶上还有一头
And then I looked up, and there's one sitting right on top of me.
你拍到了吗？我想是的
Did you get it? I think so. Hope so.
如果没有，我们都会被炒鱿鱼的
If not, then we're both fired!
花了18天，几百次潜水
It's taken 18 days and hundreds of dives,
最终，摄制组能够拍到
but at last the team have been able to reveal a secret
鲜为人知的鲸鱼的秘密
of these whales' lives that few people have ever seen.